<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
    <id>https://nimbus.team/</id>
    <title>Nimbus Blog</title>
    <updated>2022-12-30T10:00:00.000Z</updated>
    <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
    <link rel="alternate" href="https://nimbus.team/"/>
    <subtitle>Nimbus Blog</subtitle>
    <icon>https://nimbus.team/theme/image/favicon.ico</icon>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Nimbus client 2022 year-end recap]]></title>
        <id>https://nimbus.team/nimbus-2022-recap</id>
        <link href="https://nimbus.team/nimbus-2022-recap"/>
        <updated>2022-12-30T10:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[As 2022 winds down, the Nimbus research team reflects on another year of building the infrastructure needed to maximally decentralize the Ethereum network.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p></p><div class="wrapper_SWrM active_qZD5"><img loading="lazy" alt="header-image" src="/assets/images/header-775b2b79f51f11d203571a78ad36ff49.jpeg" width="2000" height="1339" class="img_ev3q"><button class="fullscreenButton_Bocn lsd-icon-button lsd-icon-button--medium lsd-icon-button--outlined"><div class="icon_S7Kx dark_qPiS m_thRi"><svg width="14" height="14" viewBox="0 0 14 14" fill="none" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" role="img"><path d="M1.75 2.917V5.25h1.167V2.917H5.25V1.75H2.917A1.17 1.17 0 0 0 1.75 2.917ZM2.917 8.75H1.75v2.333a1.17 1.17 0 0 0 1.167 1.167H5.25v-1.167H2.917V8.75Zm8.166 2.333H8.75v1.167h2.333a1.17 1.17 0 0 0 1.167-1.167V8.75h-1.167v2.333Zm0-9.333H8.75v1.167h2.333V5.25h1.167V2.917a1.17 1.17 0 0 0-1.167-1.167Z" fill="#fff"></path></svg></div></button></div><p></p><p>As 2022 winds down, the Nimbus research team reflects on another year of building the infrastructure needed to maximally decentralize the Ethereum network. Here's our recap of updates to the Nimbus consensus client over the past 12 months.</p><h2 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="nimbus-2022-unpacked">Nimbus' 2022 unpacked<a href="#nimbus-2022-unpacked" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Nimbus' 2022 unpacked" title="Direct link to Nimbus' 2022 unpacked">​</a></h2><p>The broader Ethereum ecosystem enjoyed a momentous 2022. Taking center stage, of course, was the Mainnet Merge — arguably the most ambitious software update ever orchestrated.</p><p>This year has been equally important for the Nimbus client. Among the 20 major and minor releases shipped, there were several significant improvements, changes and feature updates made to the Nimbus client in the last 12 months.</p><p>Some of 2022's key highlights include:</p><ol><li><p>The long-awaited <a href="https://github.com/status-im/nimbus-eth2/issues/3088" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">split client mode</a>. This mode enables a more flexible setup: running the Nimbus validator client independently of the beacon node. Through the validator client, advanced node operators such as institutional users and pool operators can take advantage of features like redundant beacon nodes, enhanced validator privacy and distributed keystores. Meanwhile, existing users can still use the streamlined stand-alone beacon node setup, as this mode of operation is continued to be supported and improved.  </p></li><li><p>Marked enhancements leading up to a successful Ethereum Mainnet Merge and the stable performance of Nimbus in the post-merge network.</p></li><li><p>Support for <a href="https://nimbus.guide/trusted-node-sync.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">trusted node sync</a> (also known as checkpoint sync).  </p></li><li><p>Support for <a href="https://nimbus.guide/external-block-builder.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">external block builders</a> — aka MEV — leading up to the Merge.  </p></li><li><p>Support for the Ethereum-defined REST API endpoints for light client sync.  </p></li><li><p>Beta release for the <a href="https://nimbus.guide/el-light-client.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Nimbus stand-alone light client</a>. It can be used to run any execution client without requiring a full-blown beacon node.  </p></li><li><p>Improved metrics to <a href="https://nimbus.guide/validator-monitor.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">track validator activity</a>.  </p></li><li><p>Continued improvement in <a href="https://github.com/status-im/nimbus-eth2/releases/tag/v22.12.0" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">client efficiency</a>. Now Nimbus requires less CPU, lower bandwidth and smaller memory space.  </p></li><li><p>Support for the <a href="https://nimbus.guide/keymanager-api.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Keymanager API</a> and remote keystores. With the Keymanager API, users can add, remove and migrate validators on the fly.  </p></li><li><p>Significant improvement in the <a href="https://nimbus.guide/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Nimbus guide</a> in terms of content and coverage.</p></li></ol><p>The Nimbus team is grateful to the many contributors, community champions and users who collectively pushed for greater client diversity in the network, shared valuable feedback and celebrated each milestone with us.</p><p>As we conclude the Year of the Panda, we look forward to the Year of the Owl alongside the community.</p><p><em>Check our blog and follow our social channels to stay up to date with all the latest Nimbus ecosystem developments:</em></p><ul><li><p><a href="https://our.status.im/tag/nimbus/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Blog</a></p></li><li><p><a href="https://twitter.com/ethnimbus" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Twitter</a></p></li><li><p><a href="https://discord.com/invite/qnjVyhatUa" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Discord</a></p></li><li><p><a href="https://github.com/status-im" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">GitHub</a></p></li></ul>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Status</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Unbundling the Nimbus consensus client - Part one]]></title>
        <id>https://nimbus.team/unbundling-nimbus-client-1</id>
        <link href="https://nimbus.team/unbundling-nimbus-client-1"/>
        <updated>2022-12-30T09:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[Nimbus has released a production-ready version of its validator client, addressing a key demand from node operators and advanced users.]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p></p><div class="wrapper_SWrM active_qZD5"><img loading="lazy" alt="header-image" src="/assets/images/header-a5dcc529d042bd0477eb42a7d01adebd.jpeg" width="2000" height="1335" class="img_ev3q"><button class="fullscreenButton_Bocn lsd-icon-button lsd-icon-button--medium lsd-icon-button--outlined"><div class="icon_S7Kx dark_qPiS m_thRi"><svg width="14" height="14" viewBox="0 0 14 14" fill="none" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" role="img"><path d="M1.75 2.917V5.25h1.167V2.917H5.25V1.75H2.917A1.17 1.17 0 0 0 1.75 2.917ZM2.917 8.75H1.75v2.333a1.17 1.17 0 0 0 1.167 1.167H5.25v-1.167H2.917V8.75Zm8.166 2.333H8.75v1.167h2.333a1.17 1.17 0 0 0 1.167-1.167V8.75h-1.167v2.333Zm0-9.333H8.75v1.167h2.333V5.25h1.167V2.917a1.17 1.17 0 0 0-1.167-1.167Z" fill="#fff"></path></svg></div></button></div><p></p><p>Nimbus has released a production-ready version of its validator client, addressing a key demand from node operators and advanced users. The client is highly performant and requires low resources, allowing it to run on a range of devices — from embedded systems to enterprise servers.</p><p>By default, the Nimbus consensus client's design allows validators to be run directly from the beacon node, simplifying validator setup. This makes it an ideal choice for solo-stakers, and select node operators that want to use the Nimbus beacon node. However, it made it difficult for operators to use Nimbus in their existing setups, which often feature one or more client beacon nodes interacting with multiple validator clients.</p><p>For example, one node operator runs a Teku beacon node with Teku and LH validator clients. Another operator runs a Vouch-based setup with four different client beacon nodes and a Vouch validator client. This also includes node operators in the Rocket Pool network that run several mini-pools. Each operator has fine-tuned their setup for redundancy, performance and resource consistency. It was understandably challenging for these users to directly use the default Nimbus setup of an integrated beacon node and validator client, which would mean a completely different stack to maintain and manage.</p><p>Release v22.11.0 allows users to run the Nimbus validator client independently with beacon nodes from other clients, giving operators greater flexibility and the ability to introduce Nimbus into their existing setups with minimal change. This configuration is ideal for operators running hundreds to thousands of validators.</p><p>Additionally, the new release includes improvements and fixes. For example, the beacon node is now compatible with validator clients taking advantage of the /eth/v1/beacon/blinded_blocks endpoint, and enables much faster loading of the validator keystore during startup.</p><p>Nimbus's privacy characteristics, including its low public profile and support for publishing blocks to separate nodes (such that the validator cannot be matched to its IP address by listening to attestation traffic), make it an attractive choice for advanced users and node operators.</p><p>The Nimbus team will continue to support and improve the standalone beacon node setup for individual users and hope to see more operators include the Nimbus validator client in their fleet to improve overall client diversity across the Ethereum network.</p><p>Check our blog and follow our social channels to stay up to date with all the latest Nimbus ecosystem developments:</p><ul><li><p><a href="https://our.status.im/tag/nimbus/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Blog</a></p></li><li><p><a href="https://twitter.com/ethnimbus" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Twitter</a></p></li><li><p><a href="https://discord.com/invite/qnjVyhatUa" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Discord</a></p></li><li><p><a href="https://github.com/status-im" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">GitHub</a></p></li></ul>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Status</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Nimbus - checkpoint sync, era files, Vouch]]></title>
        <id>https://nimbus.team/nimbus-update-march</id>
        <link href="https://nimbus.team/nimbus-update-march"/>
        <updated>2022-03-02T10:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[header-image]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p></p><div class="wrapper_SWrM active_qZD5"><img loading="lazy" alt="header-image" src="/assets/images/header-775b2b79f51f11d203571a78ad36ff49.jpeg" width="2000" height="1339" class="img_ev3q"><button class="fullscreenButton_Bocn lsd-icon-button lsd-icon-button--medium lsd-icon-button--outlined"><div class="icon_S7Kx dark_qPiS m_thRi"><svg width="14" height="14" viewBox="0 0 14 14" fill="none" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" role="img"><path d="M1.75 2.917V5.25h1.167V2.917H5.25V1.75H2.917A1.17 1.17 0 0 0 1.75 2.917ZM2.917 8.75H1.75v2.333a1.17 1.17 0 0 0 1.167 1.167H5.25v-1.167H2.917V8.75Zm8.166 2.333H8.75v1.167h2.333a1.17 1.17 0 0 0 1.167-1.167V8.75h-1.167v2.333Zm0-9.333H8.75v1.167h2.333V5.25h1.167V2.917a1.17 1.17 0 0 0-1.167-1.167Z" fill="#fff"></path></svg></div></button></div><p></p><p><em>(image of the <a href="https://en.m.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lennon_Wall" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Lennon Wall</a> courtesy of <a href="https://ifmsa.org/wall-peace-freedom/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">IFMSA</a>)</em>  </p><p><em>As these notes were being written, Putin's senseless war in Ukraine left nobody untouched and Status is no exception: Our Ukrainian contributors have been forced into bomb shelters with their families as brutalities increase: here are several ways that you can help: <a href="https://hrf.org/how-to-support-ukrainians/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://hrf.org/how-to-support-ukrainians/</a></em>  </p><p><em>In addition, &nbsp;a growing number of civilians in Russia and Ukraine are using the Tor project to communicate, access news, and get around censorship. You can help them by setting up a Tor bridge: <a href="https://community.torproject.org/relay/setup/bridge/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://community.torproject.org/relay/setup/bridge/</a></em></p><p>Two weeks ago we published Nimbus <code>v1.7.0</code>, a particularly feature-packed <a href="https://github.com/status-im/nimbus-eth2/releases/tag/v1.7.0" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">release</a> for our consensus layer client.  </p><blockquote><p>"So far, so good" <a href="https://t.co/g7L62tq8jy" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://t.co/g7L62tq8jy</a> <a href="https://t.co/ahshpXUZaq" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">pic.twitter.com/ahshpXUZaq</a></p><p>— Jacek Sieka (@jcksie) <a href="https://twitter.com/jcksie/status/1494381339273056259?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">February 17, 2022</a></p></blockquote><p>If you haven't done so already, we encourage you to view the <a href="https://github.com/status-im/nimbus-eth2/releases/tag/v1.7.0" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">full release notes</a> for all the gory details.  </p><p>There are a handful of important topics however, that were not covered in the notes that we feel are worth exploring in longer form.</p><p>In particular, we'd like to open up a discussion on <strong>how to improve the security of checkpoint sync</strong>, and another on <strong>how to go about fetching historical data queries in a post EIP-4444 world.</strong></p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="insecura-network-or-how-to-exploit-checkpoint-sync">#<a href="#insecura-network-or-how-to-exploit-checkpoint-sync">Insecura network (or how to exploit checkpoint sync)</a><a href="#insecura-network-or-how-to-exploit-checkpoint-sync" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to insecura-network-or-how-to-exploit-checkpoint-sync" title="Direct link to insecura-network-or-how-to-exploit-checkpoint-sync">​</a></h3><blockquote><p>Oh no! A malicious duck has taken over 12000 validator keys from a large custodial operator on the <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/eth2?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">#eth2</a> pyrmont network, and is now offering a much more master-node oriented vision for the beacon chain, named "insecura" - what happened here?</p><p>— Jacek Sieka (@jcksie) <a href="https://twitter.com/jcksie/status/1484632785671397379?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">January 21, 2022</a></p></blockquote><p>One of the infamous attacks on Proof-of-Stake is the so-called long-range attack, where keys that have been compromised are used to create a new history that honest nodes (who have been offline for a sufficient amount of time) accept as valid.</p><blockquote><p>I don't think that's right, eg if you have a long-range PoS attack where somebody gathered up keys from 3 years ago to make a new history, everybody knows which chain is legit and which is the dodgy chain, but you have to look at evidence outside the protocol to prove it</p><p>— Edmund Edgar (@edmundedgar) <a href="https://twitter.com/edmundedgar/status/1151042417665159168?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">July 16, 2019</a></p></blockquote><p>How could this happen in practice? The long and the short of it is that the beacon chain has a liveness mechanism which exits inactive validators. It's possible for a minority player to abuse this mechanism to create a history in which all validators except their own are forced to exit, thereby turning their minority into a majority (on their fork).</p><p>Once such a fork exists, the idea is that an attacker could then try to exploit <a href="https://blog.ethereum.org/2014/11/25/proof-stake-learned-love-weak-subjectivity/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">weak subjectivity</a> to get other nodes to accept it as authentic.</p><p>Fortunately, weak subjectivity, as originally thought out, is quite resistant to such an attack. As long as less than 1/3 of the keys at the time of the fork are compromised, the honest nodes provide a much more plausible history than the attacker's: because in contrast to the attacker's chain which contains a long period of non-finality during which the honest validators are seeing their stake leaked, the honest nodes have a finalising chain.</p><p>Even if a single attacker controls more than 2/3 of all keys that were active at the point of the hostile fork, it's not clear that they will be able to succeed in convincing the network that their alternative history is correct. In particular, if an honest node isn't being <a href="https://www.cs.bu.edu/~goldbe/projects/eclipseEth" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">eclipsed</a>, it will still likely choose the canonical chain simply because there are more peers serving it.</p><p>However, it turns out that <strong>checkpoint sync changes things quite drastically</strong>. In particular, it's not clear whether the above argument still holds. This is quite counter-intuitive. After all, why should passing in a URL rather than a hash make all that much difference to the security assumptions of the network?</p><p>As is often the case with security assumptions, the devil lies in the details. What it boils down to is the following: we've subtly shifted the expected behaviour from &nbsp;"getting a block hash from a friend" (as articulated in <a href="https://blog.ethereum.org/2014/11/25/proof-stake-learned-love-weak-subjectivity/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Vitalik's original post on Weak Subjectivity</a>) to "trusting a URL from one of a handful of centralised entities". This has important consequences.</p><p>To paraphrase Jacek here, <strong>checkpoint sync teaches users to pass a single URL from a centralised entity (think Infura or Etherscan) to the beacon node</strong>.</p><p><strong>If this URL is compromised (think a security breach at a centralised entity), an attacker can feed the client any state they wish</strong>, and the client will “believe” it as long as it passes some basic sanity checks. In particular, the attacker can pass the user a state that has finalised an alternative history (in other words, a different point from where the canonical validators are).</p><p>If a node starts syncing from this compromised state, it will end up rejecting any connections to, and blocks from, the honest and correct peers it comes across. It will only be able to accept compromised or dishonest peers, because the attacker's chain is finalised at a point which cannot be reconciled with the canonical one.</p><p>Fortunately, Jacek points out that the way this particular issue arises can be detected in a number of ways. In particular, such an attack provides us with several red flags along the way (see the <a href="https://ethresear.ch/t/insecura-my-consensus-for-the-pyrmont-network/11833" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">end of this post</a> for a full articulation).</p><p>Danny Ryan has posted some <a href="https://notes.ethereum.org/@djrtwo/ws-sync-in-practice" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">further ideas</a> on how we might go about addressing this problem. Two of the most interesting paths forward include:</p><ul><li><strong>N participant checkpoint download</strong>: instead of relying on the trustworthiness of one centralised entity, query N entities and check for unanimity</li><li><strong>Design a way for the bootnodes to include checkpoints in their published ENRs</strong> -- for example by adding an optional <code>wsr</code> (weak-subjectivity-root) field. Note that we can't simply rely on querying bootnodes since they are almost always at their peer limits. In other words, we can't assume that all clients will be able to maintain a connection to a bootnode.  </li></ul><p>We think it's time to move this discussion forward.  </p><p><em>If you'd like to get into the weeds here, be sure to check out Jacek's <a href="https://ethresear.ch/t/insecura-my-consensus-for-the-pyrmont-network/11833" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">detailed writeup</a> on ethresearch. He has actually carried out this attack on Pyrmont, and the post takes you through how this was done.</em></p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="era-files-a-proposed-solution-to-historical-data-queries">Era files (a proposed solution to historical data queries)<a href="#era-files-a-proposed-solution-to-historical-data-queries" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Era files (a proposed solution to historical data queries)" title="Direct link to Era files (a proposed solution to historical data queries)">​</a></h3><p>Ethereum clients currently store <a href="https://twitter.com/lightclients/status/1462576173213372417" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">275 GB</a> of historical data. But this data is not actually needed to validate the chain.</p><p>It's growing at a rate of around 140 GB per year, and is set to accelerate in a post-merge world. <a href="https://eips.ethereum.org/EIPS/eip-4444" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">EIP-4444</a> is a proposal that seeks to address this data bloat by having clients prune data older than 1 year.</p><p>However, some valid concerns have been voiced by the community. In particular, it's not clear how much is lost from preventing nodes from serving historical data over the p2p layer (something EIP-4444 explicitly mandates).  </p><blockquote><p>I used to have the ability to download and validate the full history and state just by setting a flag in geth. With these changes, default nodes will refuse to serve it to me. It may not matter for ”most”, but some of us care about it and do it.</p><p>— Eric Wall (@ercwl) <a href="https://twitter.com/ercwl/status/1466459300096794627?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">December 2, 2021</a></p></blockquote><p>In light of these concerns, Jacek's recent Era files proposal (see a <a href="https://github.com/status-im/nimbus-eth2/pull/3394" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">draft PR here</a>) can be seen as a middle ground of sorts.  </p><blockquote><p>In <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/eth?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">#eth</a>, it's widely recognized that having every node sync the full history via p2p is not sustainable, and proposals like rent and EIP-4444 aim to put bounds on what "live" clients must support. However, it's also widely recognized that the historical data is useful! 1/n</p><p>— Jacek Sieka (@jcksie) <a href="https://twitter.com/jcksie/status/1493524432719073284?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">February 15, 2022</a></p></blockquote><p>What exactly is an era file? To borrow Jacek's words, an era file is simply a day of blocks followed by the data needed to recreate consensus at that point: <strong>if you have a synced node that knows the current beacon chain head, the data in era files can be used to recreate the fully verified historical state for that time range.</strong></p><p>Era files, once created, are easily identifiable, immutable and idempotent: <strong>anyone with a fully synced node can create and/or verify one</strong>, and they can be shared by untrusted third-parties without introducing any new security problems.</p><p>Importantly, in an era file future the database remains as the source of truth for security purposes -- it stores the latest synced head root which in turn determines where a node "starts" its consensus participation. The era directory however can be freely shared between nodes / people without any (significant) security implications, assuming the era files are consistent (i.e. not broken).  </p><p>It's important to point out that, for now, era files cover only consensus -- in other words, not the full Ethereum state.</p><p>Post-merge, they'll start covering block data, but still won't cover the Ethereum state. Supporting the full EIP 4444 world is an open research topic. But focusing on consensus solves an important part of the problem: that is, knowing which state is relevant; this turns the broader problem into a tractable one.</p><p>Ideas for future improvements include serving the era files via REST: unlike the current implementation which downloads block by block, downloading an era at a time would almost entirely cut out request overhead.</p><p>One natural question to ask is how do era files affect the disk storage requirements for nodes?</p><p>It turns that the answer depends on the type of node you're running, as well as on how the relevant metaparameters are chosen.</p><blockquote><p>today (~1TB) to get "mostly equivalent" functionality, but more importantly, it stops growing there, by and large, for the "normal" participant .. light nodes would use a lot less etc..</p><p>— Jacek Sieka (@jcksie) <a href="https://twitter.com/jcksie/status/1493567566178103299?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">February 15, 2022</a></p></blockquote><p>We'd love to hear some thoughtful feedback at this stage. Is this a good idea or not? Where can it be improved? What is it missing?</p><p><em>Additionally, we believe era files (or something similar) have a role to play at the execution (eth1) level. These (torrented) files could then be used to seed <a href="https://our.status.im/nimbus-fluffly/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">the Portal network</a>. In fact, the Portal network has recently shifted priority, from working on State network to chain history, mostly due to EIP-4444. See <a href="https://snakecharmers.ethereum.org/the-aperture-vol-4/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">here</a> for a general update.<br></em></p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="a-libp2p-protocol-for-light-client-sync">A libp2p protocol for light client sync<a href="#a-libp2p-protocol-for-light-client-sync" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to A libp2p protocol for light client sync" title="Direct link to A libp2p protocol for light client sync">​</a></h3><p>We've published a <a href="https://github.com/status-im/nimbus-eth2/pull/3341" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">draft implementation</a> of our proposed (server side) libp2p protocol for light client sync.</p><blockquote><p>If one had to pick one PR to tell the story why <a href="https://twitter.com/ethnimbus?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@ethnimbus</a> was started as a project, this for sure comes close.. <a href="https://t.co/gnJV4Vnr6m" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://t.co/gnJV4Vnr6m</a></p><p>— Jacek Sieka (@jcksie) <a href="https://twitter.com/jcksie/status/1493497173555748865?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">February 15, 2022</a></p></blockquote><p>Light clients require full nodes to serve additional data so that they can stay in sync with the network. This draft contains a new launch option <code>--serve-light-client-data</code> which allows a full node to collect and disseminate the relevant data to light clients.</p><p>It's an implementation of our <a href="https://github.com/ethereum/consensus-specs/pull/2802" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">recent contribution</a> to the consensus specs.</p><p>For some context, the Altair specs needed updating, because while they did define structures to aid light client development, they were missing the network protocol definition.</p><p>In order to fill this gap, Etan <a href="https://github.com/ethereum/consensus-specs/pull/2802" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">introduced a libp2p based protocol</a> to allow light clients to sync to the latest <code>BeaconBlockHeader</code> in a trustless and decentralised manner. This builds on top of prior work from both <a href="https://github.com/ethereum/consensus-specs/pull/2267" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Hsiao-Wei Wang</a> and <a href="https://github.com/ethereum/consensus-specs/pull/2786" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Jin Huang</a>. You can <a href="https://github.com/status-im/nimbus-eth2/pull/3341" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">keep track of Etan's PR here</a>.</p><p><em><strong>Useful context:</strong> towards the end of last year, we wrote about <a href="https://our.status.im/light-nodes-ethereum-endgame/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">how crucial light clients are to a post-merge Ethereum</a>. In a separate post we also touched on how this will be <a href="https://our.status.im/nimbus-consensus-layer-2122/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">an area of focus</a> for us going forward.</em></p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="vouch-support">Vouch support<a href="#vouch-support" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Vouch support" title="Direct link to Vouch support">​</a></h3><p>Last, but not least, we are now fully compatible with Vouch! A big shout out to Jim who has tirelessly been helping us test, stress and verify compatibility of our <a href="https://nimbus.guide/rest-api.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">REST API</a> implementation.  </p><blockquote><p>Just released Vouch 1.4.0 with support for <a href="https://twitter.com/ethnimbus?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@ethnimbus</a>. Excited to add another beacon node to the mix.</p><p>— Jim McDonald (@jgm) <a href="https://twitter.com/jgm/status/1495823836704653325?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">February 21, 2022</a></p></blockquote><p>Since Vouch seems to be becoming a standard of sorts for staking providers, this is great news for client diversity: it's now seamless for providers that use Vouch to add Nimbus as an alternative client.  </p><p>Vouch also allows for other validator clients to run with Nimbus as their beacon node. For example, <a href="https://github.com/sigp/lighthouse/pull/2980#issuecomment-1027392931" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Lighthouse has successfully run their VC with a Nimbus BN</a>.</p><p>We're currently talking with several providers regarding what they can do to add Nimbus to their fleet. If you are a provider, and considering adding Nimbus to yours, please get in touch with us at <a href="mailto:nimbus@status.im" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">nimbus@status.im</a>, or alternatively reach out to us <a href="https://discord.gg/j3nYBUeEad" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">on our discord</a>. We're more than happy to answer any questions you may have and provide you with any guidance and support you may need.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Status</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Nimbus Consensus Layer - past, present, and future]]></title>
        <id>https://nimbus.team/nimbus-consensus-layer-2122</id>
        <link href="https://nimbus.team/nimbus-consensus-layer-2122"/>
        <updated>2022-01-13T10:00:00.000Z</updated>
        <summary type="html"><![CDATA[header-image]]></summary>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p></p><div class="wrapper_SWrM active_qZD5"><img loading="lazy" alt="header-image" src="/assets/images/header-7ec6f1f71d99b03e469ef311f801437a.png" width="647" height="582" class="img_ev3q"><button class="fullscreenButton_Bocn lsd-icon-button lsd-icon-button--medium lsd-icon-button--outlined"><div class="icon_S7Kx dark_qPiS m_thRi"><svg width="14" height="14" viewBox="0 0 14 14" fill="none" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg" role="img"><path d="M1.75 2.917V5.25h1.167V2.917H5.25V1.75H2.917A1.17 1.17 0 0 0 1.75 2.917ZM2.917 8.75H1.75v2.333a1.17 1.17 0 0 0 1.167 1.167H5.25v-1.167H2.917V8.75Zm8.166 2.333H8.75v1.167h2.333a1.17 1.17 0 0 0 1.167-1.167V8.75h-1.167v2.333Zm0-9.333H8.75v1.167h2.333V5.25h1.167V2.917a1.17 1.17 0 0 0-1.167-1.167Z" fill="#fff"></path></svg></div></button></div><p></p><p><em>the image above shows 40 of our dependencies purpose built by us for Nimbus and the wider Status ecosystem</em></p><blockquote><p>It's happening! <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/eth2?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">#eth2</a> genesis is upon us - stay tuned as we prepare a release with everything necessary to run <a href="https://twitter.com/ethnimbus?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@ethnimbus</a>!  </p><p>Thanks to researchers, supporters, other client teams and the community - we're in this together!</p><p>— Nimbus (@ethnimbus) <a href="https://twitter.com/ethnimbus/status/1331116128870031360?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">November 24, 2020</a></p></blockquote><p>One year later, and we've barely had a moment to catch our breath!  </p><p>Since the launch of the Beacon chain last December, we've made a ton of improvements and added a bunch of features to our software. The difference between running a Nimbus node today and back then is night and day.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="2021-highlights">2021 Highlights<a href="#2021-highlights" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to 2021 Highlights" title="Direct link to 2021 Highlights">​</a></h3><p>Some high-level highlights from the last 12 months include:</p><ul><li>26 <a href="https://github.com/status-im/nimbus-eth2/releases" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">releases</a> without any major hiccups.  </li><li>A close to perfect track record for our internal fleet of validators.  </li><li>The first client to release both <a href="https://our.status.im/nimbus-update-v1-0-7-release/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">doppelganger detection</a> and batched attestation verification.  </li><li>Successfully shifting the narrative around <a href="https://our.status.im/the-importance-of-client-diversity/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">the importance of client diversity</a> and <a href="https://our.status.im/ethereum-is-green/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Ethereum's green credentials</a>.  </li><li><a href="https://eips.ethereum.org/EIPS/eip-3076" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Influencing the direction</a> and making <a href="https://github.com/ethereum/consensus-specs/pull/2746#pullrequestreview-817674843" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">contributions</a> to both the spec and EIPs.  </li><li>Pushing the limits of what is possible with respect to both CPU and memory usage.</li></ul><p>As we touched on in our <a href="https://our.status.im/light-nodes-ethereum-endgame/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">last post</a>, Nimbus' resource efficiency is not just a nice to have. If decentralisation is <a href="https://twitter.com/jadler0/status/1433985695396282372?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw%7Ctwcamp%5Etweetembed%7Ctwterm%5E1433985695396282372%7Ctwgr%5E%7Ctwcon%5Es1_&amp;ref_url=https%3A%2F%2Four.status.im%2Fp%2Fdbab5f30-9e0b-49fb-84c7-ef7adb9d9455%2F" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">the cost to run a full node</a>, then resource efficiency is absolutely <a href="https://our.status.im/light-nodes-ethereum-endgame/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">crucial to maintaining a sufficiently robust and decentralised network</a>. This is especially true in a post-merge world in which the community is expected to <a href="https://vitalik.ca/general/2021/12/06/endgame.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">keep block producers in check</a>.</p><p>To borrow Dankrad's words:</p><blockquote><p>I don't care about the absolute number of nodes.<br>
<!-- -->I care about the amount of transaction value that is fully secured. That means the user is either running a full node or a fraud proof-protected light client.</p><p>— Dankrad Feist (@dankrad) <a href="https://twitter.com/dankrad/status/1415424096024858624?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">July 14, 2021</a></p></blockquote><p>Today, Nimbus is able to run performantly on a single core of a Raspberry Pi 4 while also running Geth, RocketPool and monitoring software (Prometheus + Grafana) in the background. We expect this to keep holding true post merge.</p><blockquote><p>We are on it, <a href="https://twitter.com/go_ethereum?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@go<!-- -->_<!-- -->ethereum</a> Geth + <a href="https://twitter.com/ethnimbus?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@ethnimbus</a> in the same <a href="https://twitter.com/Raspberry_Pi?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@Raspberry<!-- -->_<!-- -->Pi</a>. <a href="https://t.co/s2lg573Njh" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://t.co/s2lg573Njh</a></p><p>— Ethereum on ARM 🦇🔊 (@EthereumOnARM) <a href="https://twitter.com/EthereumOnARM/status/1407339958046765061?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">June 22, 2021</a></p></blockquote><p>Perhaps one final thing worth mentioning here is that our language of choice, Nim, has required us to build out nearly all the <a href="https://nimbus.team/docs/libraries.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">libraries</a> we rely on ourselves. In the light of recent NPM and Pypi registry attacks, we believe this to be a key strength of ours relative to other clients.  </p><p>We have very few external dependencies. And these dependencies are all fuzzed, audited, formally verified, &nbsp;or have similar rock solid guarantees.</p><blockquote><p>Curious which libraries Nimbus depends on? <!-- -->`<!-- -->make deps<!-- -->`<!-- --> shows the full transitive list with the exact version, including the <a href="https://twitter.com/nim_lang?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@nim<!-- -->_<!-- -->lang</a> compiler - there is 61 of them right now, counting several that are used only for testing - 40 were purpose-built by <a href="https://twitter.com/ethstatus?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@ethstatus</a>! <a href="https://t.co/L407vmQKZK" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">pic.twitter.com/L407vmQKZK</a></p><p>— Nimbus (@ethnimbus) <a href="https://twitter.com/ethnimbus/status/1480500108810674176?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">January 10, 2022</a></p></blockquote><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="icing-on-the-cake">Icing on the cake<a href="#icing-on-the-cake" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Icing on the cake" title="Direct link to Icing on the cake">​</a></h3><p>Having thought deeply about, and written extensively on <a href="https://medium.com/dappnode/guardians-of-ethereum-a-validator-dao-proposal-d82e76231b45" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">the importance of trustless staking pools</a>, the icing on the cake for us last year was, without a doubt, the launch of Rocket Pool.</p><p>After everything the team has been through, notably the <a href="https://medium.com/rocket-pool/the-merge-0x02-mev-and-the-future-of-the-protocol-c7451337ec40" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">drama</a> around <code>0x02</code>, it was truly wonderful to see their vision of a trustless and community owned staking pool start to take shape.</p><p>We were especially happy to see that, by some estimates, Nimbus is the second most popular Rocket Pool client.</p><blockquote><p>218 <a href="https://twitter.com/Rocket_Pool?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">@Rocket<!-- -->_<!-- -->Pool</a> proposals, four weeks in: <a href="https://t.co/HrLZrjCWWC" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">pic.twitter.com/HrLZrjCWWC</a></p><p>— superphiz.eth 🦇🔊🐼 (@superphiz) <a href="https://twitter.com/superphiz/status/1467978840278503429?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">December 6, 2021</a></p></blockquote><p>Thank you Joe Clapis for everything you've done to red-pill the community into using Nimbus :)</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="zooming-in-on-last-quarter">Zooming in on last quarter<a href="#zooming-in-on-last-quarter" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Zooming in on last quarter" title="Direct link to Zooming in on last quarter">​</a></h3><p>In case you haven't kept up with our <a href="https://github.com/status-im/nimbus-eth2/releases" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">latest releases</a>, arguably the three most important features shipped last quarter were:</p><ul><li>Support for the <code>web3signer</code> protocol (currently in BETA)</li><li>A feature complete <code>rest</code> API (still ironing out a few issues)</li><li>A <code>--num-threads</code> option which allows Nimbus to take advantage of multiple CPU cores</li></ul><p><code>v1.5.5</code> alone saw three significant optimisations worth highlighting here:</p><ul><li>A 6x speed-up in epoch processing</li><li>A 2x speed up in Altair block processing</li><li>A 12% reduction in outgoing GossipSub traffic (bandwidth reduction).</li></ul><blockquote><p>A calm-after-the-altair-storm release with lots of polish across the board - big drop in outgoing network traffic thanks to an elegant libp2p optimization, more flexibility in the REST interface allows you to use Nimbus with a growing amount of 3rd party tools, web3signer.. <a href="https://t.co/RTerT29ijA" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">https://t.co/RTerT29ijA</a></p><p>— Jacek Sieka (@jcksie) <a href="https://twitter.com/jcksie/status/1467938248936804356?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">December 6, 2021</a></p></blockquote><p>Both <code>web3signer</code> support and the <code>rest</code> API pave the way for wider adoption of Nimbus. <code>web3signer</code> by allowing for staking pools and other providers with a custom key handling strategy to use Nimbus. And the <code>rest</code> API by allowing for third-party validator clients such as <a href="https://www.attestant.io/posts/introducing-vouch/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Vouch</a> (or any other validator client for that matter) to use Nimbus as their beacon node.</p><p>Special thanks to Jim Mcdonald (@jgm) for helping us test the REST server: It is in large part thanks to your testing that we managed to get to the finish line!</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="going-forward">Going forward<a href="#going-forward" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to Going forward" title="Direct link to Going forward">​</a></h3><p>There is so much to look forward to in 2022. Here's a quick overview of our priorities:</p><ul><li><strong>The merge, then sharding</strong>: the main focus here is on the stellar and timely execution of the <a href="https://github.com/ethereum/consensus-specs/tree/dev/specs/merge" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">merge</a> followed by the <a href="https://github.com/ethereum/consensus-specs/blob/dev/specs/sharding/beacon-chain.md" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">sharding</a> specs.</li><li><strong>Wider adoption</strong>: we have a new business development unit (welcome <a href="https://twitter.com/liftlines" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Kausha</a>l!) devoted to increasing adoption. The initial focus will be on providing support for staking pools and providers who wish to adopt Nimbus ( a number of which have already committed to running Nimbus this year).</li><li><strong>Diversity++:</strong> this will mainly involve implementing all standards which seek to promote client diversity &nbsp;(e.g. the development of cross-client UIs, migration tools, and the <a href="https://ssv.network/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">SSV</a> network).</li><li><strong>The great rebranding</strong>: we want people to realise at a glance that Nimbus is great for far more than just resource-restricted devices. And, in particular, that there are important advantages to using it for enterprise grade infrastructure. This requires rethinking our branding and how we talk about ourselves.</li><li><strong>Privacy</strong>: as part of Status, caring about privacy is in our DNA. We plan on exploring how we can leverage our work on <a href="https://rfc.vac.dev/spec/10/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Waku</a> in order to <a href="https://github.com/libp2p/specs/issues/374" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">bring more privacy to validators at the networking layer</a>.</li><li><strong>A Nimbus focused UI</strong>: we are committing serious resources towards a Nimbus UI which will be an integral part of the Status product roadmap moving forward. Our focus here is on user-friendly approaches for creating, managing, and monitoring validators (no CLI experience needed).</li></ul><p>This year will also see us increasingly focused on lowering the technical barriers to running a full node (both consensus and execution) as well as pushing forward with our <a href="https://github.com/etan-status/nimbus-eth2/compare/merkle-multiproof...etan-status:lightclient-api" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">light client implementation</a> (keep track of our progress <a href="https://github.com/status-im/nimbus-eth2/issues/2337#issuecomment-967153855" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">here</a>).</p><p>As we mentioned in our <a href="https://our.status.im/nimbus-execution-layer/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">execution layer recap</a>, one of our main design goals is to make it as easy as possible for our consensus and execution clients to be bundled into a single piece of software. With the Nimbus UI, you'll be able &nbsp;to manage and monitor your node straight from the Status Desktop app.</p><blockquote><p>I can't wait to run Nimbus straight from Status Desktop <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/hyped?src=hash&amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">#hyped</a></p><p>— Jarrad Hope (@0xc1c4da) <a href="https://twitter.com/0xc1c4da/status/1293473249347555334?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">August 12, 2020</a></p></blockquote><p><a href="https://our.status.im/light-nodes-ethereum-endgame/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Complementary to this vision</a> (and part of our longer-term UI roadmap) is an embedded light client running on your mobile phone.</p><h3 class="anchor anchorWithHideOnScrollNavbar_WYt5" id="more-thank-yous">More thank yous<a href="#more-thank-yous" class="hash-link" aria-label="Direct link to More thank yous" title="Direct link to More thank yous">​</a></h3><p>We want to end by saying a big thank you to the Ethereum Foundation for the unbelievably generous incentive program they <a href="https://blog.ethereum.org/2021/12/13/client-incentive-program/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">announced</a> towards the end of last year. We are truly humbled to be valued by you in this way.</p><p>A big thank you to all the node runners using Nimbus, without you our work would be, quite frankly, meaningless.</p><p>And, last but by no means least, a big thank you to all our <a href="https://gitcoin.co/grants/137/nimbus" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Gitcoin supporters</a>: even more important than the financial, is the moral support; the appreciation we feel from every single one of you, each GR round, keeps our spirits high when the going feels tough.  </p><p>We wish you all the very best of luck this coming year.</p>]]></content>
        <author>
            <name>Sacha</name>
        </author>
    </entry>
</feed>